Shraddha's side, welcome to concept and
coding, and today in this video we will
see an OAuth 2 implementation.
So, if you have not seen the previous
video where I have explained about what
is OAuth and what are the different
grant types, so I would highly recommend
that kindly have a look at it once
before jumping into the implementation.
Okay? So, I will give you a very very
quick recap. What is OAuth? OAuth stands
for open authorization framework. It
enables a third-party access.
Right? Secure third-party access to user
protected data.
We have a different grant types like
authorization code grant, implicit
grant, client credentials, and there are
two more, right? Which we have already
discussed in the previous video.
So, today I will do an implementation in
a Spring Boot for this authorization
code grant flow.
So, before jumping into the
implementation, let's have a quick recap
of what is authorization code grant flow
looks like.
So, consider the resource owner, which
is us, you, me. So, we have our data.
Right? Where
in let's say in one of the resource
server, let's say Gmail. We have our
data like mail, like some profile
picture,
Gmail,
email ID, username, like we have
and mobile number. We have our data
present into the Gmail. And Gmail has
one of its
authorization server also.
Okay? And this is client or Insta or you
can say that any third-party app.
Third-party app which we have to grant
access to our data, but securely. How we
can do that? We have seen that already.
So, quickly
first this third-party app has to
register themselves. Register itself
into the authorization server. Let's say
in this case with the Gmail
authorization server, they have to
register this third-party app. So, Gmail
will send them the client ID and secret,
which this third-party app will store
it.
Now, what would happen is let's say that
I am going and saying that
hey,
this third-party app, let's say Insta, I
want to sign in, but I want to sign in
using Gmail. I don't have an account on
here. The first time I'm coming and I'm
choosing sign in using Gmail.
So, what it will do is it will redirect
me to this authorization server.
Right? This third-party app redirect me
to the authorization server and it will
send the client ID also in the request.
So, what
authorization server will do,
it will give me a
username password field where the
resource owner, I have to provide my
username my password of the Gmail.
Right? Means I am providing the consent
that yes, hey Gmail,
allow
this third-party app to access my this
data.
Okay? Once I provide this,
this authorization server return the
authorization code back in the response.
Using this authorization code, this
third-party app makes another API call
to fetch the token.
Right? And inside the request, it will
pass code, uh client ID, and the secret
which it initially got.
Right? And it requests for the token.
Once it
got this all the details authorization
server, it will return back the token.
It could be the JWT token.
Possible. Right?
There are different type of token like
opaque token, JWT token. So, it might
return the token, access token.
And now using this token, it will hit
the API of this authorization server.
Let's say Gmail API. Right?
Gmail API, hey, fetch me the details of
let's say
mobile number or username and email ID.
Depend upon what the third party want
access to. Right? With this JWT access
token
with the OAuth 2 model
we can access the API and through which
we can fetch the user details.
Okay? Now it got the token. So it has in
the request it has to pass the token.
Okay? Now once this resource server got
the token, it will pass it to the
authorization server, validate it. If
it's valid
like if the token is valid, it will
return the details and based on that it
will
sure that sign-in is successful.
Okay? If it is not valid, it will throw
an error, like failure ultimately.
So this is a very high-level flow which
we have seen. Now we will implement it.
But again
before we jump into the implementation,
we have to understand what is a
difference between OAuth 2 and OIDC.
Now you can ask me, hey, what is OIDC?
Why it comes into the picture?
So again, first the difference is full
form is OAuth 2 is like open
authorization.
OIDC stand for OpenID Connect.
What is the purpose used for?
OAuth is used for authorization.
Meanwhile, OIDC is used for
authentication. What is the difference?
See
here in this OAuth 2
we grant secure third party access to
user protected data. Means
third party app, like in this case
uh we are saying Insta, can have access
to my let's say all the Gmail emails, my
calendar data, depends upon what all the
APIs are exposed.
Okay? So, it can invoke the endpoint
passing the token and fetch all my data,
protected data.
But, OIDC is mainly specific specific
for authentication only.
So, it's a layer built on top of OAuth 2
only.
And enable the third party app to verify
the identity of the user by an
authentication server.
Okay? So, understand the difference with
this.
Here, the only difference comes at this
part.
So, here it get the token, right? Once
it get the token, if you are using plain
OAuth 2,
you can use this token,
pass it to this
resource server, and you can access
whatever data you want.
Right? All the protected data you can
access of mine.
But, with the OIDC,
whatever the token you will get,
generally it is known as ID token.
ID token, which is again in the form of
JWT only, but this ID token has all the
info which is required for
authentication purpose. You don't need
to call any API
and fetch any other data.
In the OIDC, this token itself has all
the limited very minimal information
which is required just for
authentication.
Okay?
This token
ID token is not understood by
resource server.
This ID token is specifically for this
third party app only that, "Hey,
from this token you will get a minimal
information, through this you can
authenticate the user. But, this ID
token cannot be used to access my
protected data.
But, with the OAuth 2, whatever the
token you will get, with that you can
pass it to the resource server, they
understand that by passing it to
authorization server.
And then they can you can fetch the
protected data.
I hope you got the difference.
OAuth 2 is like for authorization. You
can fetch the protected data. For OIDC
only for authentication. Uh once the
token is received by the third-party
app, they don't generally pass it back
to the resource server to access more
data. The token itself has all the
information to require to authenticate.
So token is generated as access token
which is generally opaque or JWT form.
Okay. So consider like a GitLab use
case. Generally they return opaque
token.
Opaque token is uh not understood by the
third-party app. Only it is understood
by the authorization server.
Okay.
So use by third-party app to call the
resource server APIs
to access user protected data.
Okay. So that's what I told you in the
plain OAuth 2. Once the
token is received, either JWT or opaque
token.
Okay. So this token is used by the
third-party app to fetch the
to call the APIs through which they can
fetch the protected data.
But here in the token generated by OIDC
is that ID token which is
JWT form only.
Plus since it is built on top of OAuth
2, it also
get us access token also.
So it gives us both the capability. If
you want, I can go ahead and call the
API also
and fetch more information.
Otherwise, this ID token itself is
contain all the information
for authentication. So ID token is a JWT
token which is meant for third-party app
only. Remember this. I am
emphasizing on this that
it is meant for third-party app. This ID
token is not sent
to this resource server.
It is not sent. Once it get the token,
it has the minimal information. It has
the minimal user info which can be
required for authentication.
Okay, we will see that.
But first remember the difference. So
the scope The scope is like read, write
in the plain OAuth 2.
In the plain OAuth 2, generally scope is
at read, write. Like you can even call
post APIs for writing.
You got reading means you can allowing
the third-party app to call the APIs
only get APIs.
Or you want to call even allowing them
to call the write APIs.
Here it is OpenID.
The scope is OpenID. OpenID means it
indicate the authorization server that
this third-party app is only want to
authenticate user.
Okay? So there is a scope called OpenID.
When the ID token is generated by the
authentication server, authorization
server,
it will contain very minimal information
in the token JWT.
Okay? Which is required only for
authentication.
No read, write access is given. In the
token itself, very minimal information
is sent.
Okay? If the difference is clear,
let's jump into the
implementation.
So what is the step one?
Step one is
the third-party app. Now in this case,
who is the third-party app? Our Spring
Boot app, which we which we are writing.
So third-party app, we have to register
it so that in the response we can get
client ID and secret key.
So third-party app registration to
authentication server. This is the first
step. So third-party app is our a Boot
app.
Authorization server, currently we can
pick a Auth0 and GitLab.
Okay, so we can register ourselves and
get the client ID and the client secret.
So, we'll see that. So, here if you see
if you open the GitLab,
there you will see
application. In the settings, you will
see application. Inside that
application, you give the application
name. I give my Spring Boot app.
The redirect URI, right? The redirect
URI is that here if you see
once the owner authenticate and provide
consent,
it redirect. It calls a redirect URI and
passes the authorization code in the
response.
So, we have to set that redirect URI.
And the scope which we have to select.
So, I have select the open ID.
Because I am only interested in
authentication.
Okay? So, only also gives read-only
access to the user profile.
Right? So, not much very minimal
information.
Grant permission to authenticate with
GitLab using OpenID Connect. So,
specifically for authentication.
And once you save the application, you
will get client ID and the client secret
which you can copy it from here.
Okay?
Similarly,
in the OAuth
Auth0 registration,
what we can do is we have to provide the
name.
Okay? And here we have all the OIDC is
uh turned it on. It also provide what
signature algorithm which we have to
use. I choose RS256 RS256, which is like
a private public key. And uh
like in the JWT,
whatever the signing algorithm would be.
So, here I'm defining that one. We have
already seen that in the JWT
uh part.
And ultimately, I will get my client ID
and the client secret here.
Okay? So,
we can see here like So, here if you
see, I open the GitLab. So, now in this
part, if you go to the settings, click
on edit profile.
Okay? So, there you will see
application.
If you click on the application,
you will see this like you can add an
application. I can add a new application
also where you can give a name, redirect
URI, and what is the scope you wanted to
select.
And once you do save application, it
would be like
this it will come like your
client ID and the secret. Secret is like
you can copy it one one time. After
that, it will remove from here just for
safety purpose. So, you can renew the
secret. Okay? So, the old secret would
become invalid. And the scope I choose
is open ID, authenticate only.
Similarly, for the Auth0 also, it's the
same thing. You can open Auth0 and you
can create add new application and then
you can add it like this.
Okay? So, here what I'm doing is I am
registering myself, my application, and
I'm getting a client ID and the client
secret.
Okay? So, this ID, what I have to do is
I have to store it.
Okay? So, in the application.properties,
I am saving these details.
Now,
okay, we'll come to the pom, but here if
you see,
these are the configuration. These are
the for the GitLab.
And this is for the Auth0.
Okay? So, two authorization servers I am
adding. So, this is my client ID. This
is my client secret.
What is the scope? Open ID. Okay? What
is the grant type I am using?
Authorization code. Whatever the
different grant type we have, right? In
OAuth2, you can use anything, but
currently I'm implementing authorization
code.
Redirect URI I have set like, okay, this
is the API which uh
authorization server has to call when
they have to return me the authorization
code. So, redirect URI
authorization URI is something which
like uh I have to invoke. So, here in
this case, right?
See this part.
So, once this part uh
this part. This is the URL. This is the
authorize
This is the authorize URL.
Okay? And then I when I have to ask for
token, this is the token URI.
Okay? So, this is all the URIs I'm
setting. So, what is the redirect URI,
authorization URI, what is the token
URI?
What is the issuer URI? Issuer Issuer
URI is nothing but like what Who is your
authorization server?
Okay? And JWK set URI is something like,
where is the public key
is stored?
Like whatever the token you will
receive, we have to sign We have to
verify that token, right? So,
in asymmetric encryption,
the authorization server use the private
key to sign it, and we have to verify it
using public key. So, public key has to
be read from where? That URL.
Okay? So, these are mostly very very
standard URLs.
Right? And mostly here, if you see,
and in the configuration your key, this
part only change.
GitLab. Now, here we have Auth0.
So, if you have any other Gmail, so only
all the links would be same. Only here
Gmail would come. Or whatever their
authorization server name would be, that
would come. Okay? So, these are
generally known as registration
ID.
So, registration ID I have two. One is
GitLab, and one is Auth0.
Okay? And these are the
URIs which are present.
Okay?
These are also very, very standard URIs.
So, like whatever the authorization
server which you have, and then these
endpoints remains the same.
Okay? So, you will see mostly the
endpoints remains the same. No not much
difference. Only your authorization
server
becomes different. After that, the
endpoints become mostly the same.
Okay? So, we have added this two
information.
We have added this two authorization
server, and we have to add this pom.xml
a Spring Boot Starter OAuth2 client.
With this dependency,
all the libraries like which understand
this configuration, there are certain
specific OAuth2 filters code that would
come to in our project.
Okay? So, we require this pom. We added
this application.properties.
Uh okay? And in the securityconfig.java,
okay? So, here in this case, if you see
that, we want OAuth2 login. We don't
want form. We don't want basic.
We want OAuth2
login customize with default.
Okay?
So, we have added three things. pom,
application.properties,
and securityconfig where we have tell
the Spring Boot that we want to go ahead
with the OAuth2 login.
And we have just added very, very basic
controller, not required. Just like one
default page.
Because here we have set that, right?
Customizer with default. So, once the
authentication is success, it will try
to hit the
default page, localhost
8080 and the default default page. So,
that's where I just written hello, you
are logged in.
And one specific APIs, if that one would
be hit, it will say that fetch the
details
fetch the details successfully.
So, very basic controller I have
written.
So,
till now, what we have done is we have
just registered over app.
And based on that registration,
we have
set up the application.properties.
Palm, we have added the OAuth2
dependencies. Security config we have
tell to the Spring Boot that we want to
go ahead with the OAuth2.
And the basic controllers we have
written.
Now, let's see. Let's try.
Only notice one thing that I have not
created any user in the Spring Boot app.
User is not there. My detail is present
into GitLab or Auth0.
Right? But not in the Spring Boot app.
So, I am starting the application
server. My application server is a
started.
Now, I am hitting localhost 8080
URL.
Since
it is like
any request we have to authenticate, it
will take me to the default login
endpoint. Since we are using
OAuth2 login
and customize with default. So, with
default login page is \slash} login
only.
Okay?
So, it will take me to the login
endpoint. So, two See, you will see this
page.
Two login with OAuth2 two authorization
server. First and second. First is
Auth0, second is GitLab.
So, where this information is coming
from? This information which we have set
into the
application.properties.
One is GitLab, another is Auth0. And the
authorization server is this issuer URI,
gitlab.com.
And this Auth0 generally give us a
custom authorization server URI. So,
this URI.
Okay.
Now, you can choose anything which you
wanted to log in.
Right? So, now let's say that if I
choose Auth0. When I click the Auth0,
it redirect me to the Auth0 login page.
Right? Now, you see that I haven't
written any code for all this
redirection and all. It's working now.
So, it automatically when I click here,
it redirect me to the Auth0 login page.
Log in to this to continue my Spring
Boot app.
And here I have to provide my email
address and password.
Once I did this, what what is the next
step? So,
first is registration,
then it will give me client ID and
secret. Done. Then what is the next
step? Like uh
I have to call the authorize endpoint.
So, this is the authorize endpoint. Once
you click here,
it call the authorize endpoint.
It goes to the authorization server.
Authorization server will show me
username password page, and it redirect
me to the
it redirect me with the authorization
code.
And using that authorization code, I
will pass the token you
endpoint, and ultimately I will get the
token.
And from there, it will use the token,
fetch the details,
and whatever the detail it will get, it
will
authenticate myself.
So, all this thing happening in behind.
Okay, once I provided the username
password,
it will redirect URI will get invoked.
And after this, all this thing happening
at the behind, and ultimately I am get
logged in.
We will see that everything what is
happening in behind. Right? If you see,
I'm able to log in successfully. If I
hit /user endpoint,
I'm able to call it.
So, this is the second endpoint, right?
That is also working properly, even
though I have mentioned all the requests
should be authenticated.
So, how it is working, right? I have
just given
pom, application.properties,
security config. All I tell to the
Spring Boot that use OAuth 2 login with
default.
And rest
everything works out of the box.
Right?
With these three things, everything
works fine.
So, a Spring Boot Security framework
provide the complete functionality of
OAuth 2 protocol.
We don't have to code anything.
But, here is one twist.
When I tried to access this /user from
the browser,
it is working, right? But, the same API
when I'm hitting through Postman,
it is asking me to like again log in. It
is not yet logged in.
Why?
Why so?
Because a Spring Boot assume that
OAuth 2 login would be done on a
browser.
So, by default it creates session.
In browser, we it creates a session.
That's why it is working.
And here I am not passing any in the
cookie what is the session ID. So,
that's why it is asking me to log in
again.
Then you you one question comes to your
mind, hey, then what
2 is stateful?
Right? By default, the Spring
created it as a stateful. But, we can
make it a stateless also. We will see
that.
But, first we need to see the stateful.
What exactly how it is working behind?
Till now, we we don't know how it is
working.
Till now, all we know is that
Hey, this I have added palm, I have
added application.properties and
security conflict. That's all.
It worked out.
But, how?
Now, let's first discover that how part.
So,
we have already covered this part,
registration part, right? This one is
clear. You can open GitLab, add
application, you can register your app.
Similarly, in Auth0 also, you can
register your app.
Now, what would happen
when I click when a user click
on my
app. So, this is now in our third-party
app is our Spring Boot app.
So, now when a user click on this
localhost:8080
login, hey, I want to login.
I have to show this two pages, right?
Two authorization server where user can
login with.
So, what internally happen is
So, default login page generating filter
get invoked.
Inside that, there is a method called
generate login HTML. So, there it has
like if it is a OAuth 2 login enabler,
we have to show this page.
And from where this get this
information? So, here if you see
something like OAuth 2
OAuth 2 authentication URL to client
name. So, when you start an application,
right? This get filled up from
application.properties.
Okay, so this is has all the
information. So, it just iterate over it
and just show this.
Okay? It just show this information.
So, now we know that okay, once I have
print the once I click on the login
URL,
how I am able to see these two things.
Okay, this filter helps in generating
this page.
Now,
when a user click on any of the link,
what would happen?
When user click on one of the
authorization server,
this endpoint would get invoked.
oauth2/authorization/registration
ID.
What is the registration ID? We have one
registration ID is this. This is known
as registration registration ID. I
already told GitLab,
auth0. Or there if you have more, these
are known as registration ID. So,
whichever link you click, that
registration ID would get append. So,
let's say if I am clicking GitLab, so /
oauth2/authorization/GitLab.
This API would get invoked.
Okay?
So,
when this endpoint get invoked,
this filter will catch it.
oauth2AuthorizationRequestRedirectFilter.java.
This filter will is also present into
the security framework
because of the dependency which we have
added.
So, now here if you see,
here we have the authorization request.
In authorization request, what we have,
we have the client ID.
I told you, right?
The client ID the third-party app in our
Spring Boot, the client ID would get
there in the request, and then it will
redirect to the authorization server.
Okay, the request got now redirected to
the authorization server.
Okay, and of
it invokes this API.
Like whatever the
registration ID you have picked,
whether
GitLab or Auth0. Depending upon that,
it will have this all the URI which it
has to invoke, and then it invokes the
authorization appropriate authorization
server.
Okay? Then authorization server, if it
is GitLab, it will ask you to provide
your username password. If it's Auth0,
again, email ID password. So, you have
to authenticate the yourself, and also
you have to authorize the Spring Boot
app that they can access my request.
So, once it is done,
once it is done,
the authorization servers calls the
redirect URI,
which we have set during
registration, we have seen that we have
set the redirect URI.
So, it will invoke the redirect URI.
Okay? And in the response, here if you
see response, they have set the code,
authorization code.
Okay?
So,
which endpoint?
This endpoint, this filter now catch
this.
OAuth2 login authentication filter.java
is the one which catch this
redirect URI.
Now, what they will do?
They will first make an authentication
object out of this response.
Okay?
And
then what they are doing is they are
calling the authenticate.
They are means passing it to the
authentication manager, and
authentication manager redirect it to
authentication provider. So, since we
are using
OpenID,
and what is the token it created? OAuth2
login authentication token.
So, this is the provider which can
handle this.
OIDC
authorization code authentication
provider.java.
So, this provider
this authenticate method ultimately for
this provider will get caught because
this can support this uh
token authentication object and also for
open ID scope, this will support it.
So, now here if you see, it do two
things.
Here till now I have authorization code.
Authorization code is there in my
this token. In token, I have already set
the authorization code. Whatever I have
got in the response.
In the authorization response, I have
got the code, right? So, I have set it
and pass it to the provider.
Now, what it will do is it is calling
invoking the token URI
of the authorization server to fetch the
token
access token response.
Okay? And it also has the ID token also.
From response, so whatever the response
the response it goes, right? From this
it fetch both access and ID token.
Okay? So, it fetches the ID token. So,
we are mostly interested in this ID
token. During authentication, we are
interested in this ID token which we get
from this response of this.
So, we take out the ID token
and return back to authentication
filter.
Okay? So, ultimately here if you see,
we call the authorized endpoint.
It return back with the
authorization code.
And after that, I invoke the token URI
internally. All happening internally. We
are user is not even knowing about it.
Okay? So, it invoke the token URI
endpoint
and it return back the ID token.
Okay. Now ID token what I have done is
So see, in the I have got the ID token.
This is how ID token. If you see that,
there is something called access token.
This is not a JWT. JWT you remember that
has three part.
Okay, so part one, part two, and part
three.
Your header, your claim, and then your
signature part.
But here if you see this token has only
there is no dot.
So this is known as opaque token.
Only authorization server understand
what it has. We don't know.
So but for OIDC ID token is is in JWT
format. If you see this is this is JWT
format.
So here when it tries to do right create
token, right? It uh
parses So in the parsing you can see the
information.
It has all my information, profile,
username,
right? It has my picture.
Like all all information it has.
Okay?
All basic information which is required
for authentication it has.
So this ID token is received
at this provider which it return back to
filter.
Okay, and filter what it does is it just
stores the token and creates an HTTP
session.
And once the session is created,
it return that login successful. And if
you see in the cookie, session is
created.
And that's why when you hit \slash}
users, now cookie has a session.
So it automatically give me an access.
So if you understand this flow,
this uh
diagram could also help you a little bit
more clarify it. So now user is clicking
the login endpoint.
Okay?
It will goes to the filter chain.
From there, it will goes to one of the
filter. First is login. So, which
filter? Default login page generating
filter will get invoked.
It will return me a list of
authorization server which it get from
the application.properties.
It's just simply return it
and shown to the user.
Now, user would be shown two things like
auth
uh auth O and uh GitLab.
Which one you want to authenticate? Now,
once a user click on one of the server,
this is the endpoint get invoked.
Auth two authorization registration ID.
In this case, it would be GitLab.
Uh the filter chain will get invoked. It
will pass the request to one of the
security filter chain. Which filter?
Auth two authorization request redirect
filter will get invoked.
It will redirect the request to the
authorization server.
Okay? And return
to the client.
But authorization server uh now
it redirected the user to this.
So, there a user has to provide username
password.
Okay?
But its flow is finished. Its flow it's
returned. So, it has returned it. It has
completed its flow, but now you user has
been redirected this where it has to
provide the username password.
Let's say GitLab, so it would be like a
GitLab page.
Once user has provided the username
page, it will redirect
call a redirect URI
with the authorization code.
Now, which filter in catches it? Auth
two login authentication filter.
It creates an authentication token
object which is a nothing but an
authentication object. It put
authorization code here.
It passes to the authorization manager.
Authorization manager passes it to the
authentication provider, which
authentication provider understand this
token and this is scope open ID is OIDC
authorization code authentication
provider.
So, this understands it.
So, what it does is it calls the token
URI of the authorization server, passes
the client ID, client secret, and
authorization code.
Okay? So, authorization server return
access token, refresh token, and ID
token in response.
So, it will return the same to the
filter.
Now, it will what filter will do?
See this. First filter is stored this
token information into in memory or two
authorization client service.
So, we can also
instead of storing in memory, we can
also store it into the DB.
We can do that.
Right? We can implement this or two
client service and we can override and
restore it into the DB how we have seen
where storing token into the DB.
Similarly, this ID token, access token
which we are getting from the
authorization server, we can store it
DB, but currently it is storing in in
memory.
And then ultimately it's create an HTTP
session
and restore this session into like
whatever the authentication object,
right? Which is coming.
That is stored into the security context
holder.
And ultimately it passes call the
\slash}
localhost:8080/endpoint.
So, it has created an HTTP session. So,
this is the all the flow happen
internally.
And now, when you click \slash} users
you are trying to access any API
since the session is created, security
context holder filter will get involved.
It will pass to the HTTP session
security context repository. It will
fetch the session.
And if the session is active, it will
grant an access.
It will grant an access.
So, here if you see that
here if you see that when the session is
set
it might not validate the token with
each request.
So, session is valid
the request has
passed through.
So, it is possible that
ID token becomes invalidated, but
session is still active. Possible,
right? Because now with every request my
session is this filter get involved.
This see that his session is present. If
session is present, it will access the
request. It is not
taking out my tokens out of this in
memory and validating that token hit
that token is valid or not.
It is not doing that.
So, this makes our OAuth stateful.
And that's the one of the reason that
when Postman when I hit, it is not able
to access it.
So, how to fix it?
We can make it a stateless.
Right? And we can return the ID token in
the response. So that the client will
pass the token and we will validate the
token every time with every request.
Can we do that with this framework?
Yes, we can do that.
Very easily.
So, what I will do is that the same flow
like
the same flow once the user
two endpoint, right?
Uh two authorization server. Let's say
one is GitLab, one is Auth0.
User has clicked this.
Okay? The same thing. My redirect filter
would get involved. It will pass this to
authorization server. Authorization
server will pass it to authorization
code. Everything same.
This will pass this
authorization code,
creates an authentication token.
Authentication object will pass to the
authentication manager with to
authentication provider.
It will reach to the OIDC provider,
which will call the token URI,
and ultimately which will return me the
token, ID token.
And when the control ultimate goes to
the filter, what the first thing it will
do? It will store it into in-memory
first. Second, it will create an HTTP
session and store it into the security
context holder.
So, in previous part, it was doing till
here.
But now, since I want to make it a
stateless, I have to return that ID
token in response.
So, this filter is already doing all
these things. Authentication filter
already doing all these things.
Now, I'm adding one additional
functionality here.
This is important.
I am returning the ID token in the
response body.
How I am doing that?
So, here if you open the OAuth 2 login
authentication filter, see that. OAuth 2
login authentication filter.
So, if we see that uh
after authentication,
its parent
attempt authentication. Something was
right. Attempt
authentication. Yeah.
So, after this
uh
OAuth 2 login authentication filter,
control will come here.
What it does is it will create a
session, which we have seen here. So,
let me zoom it a bit.
Okay. So, it will first session
strategy. So, it will create a session.
We can't change it. This framework is
already doing that. We can't delete that
don't create a session.
After that, it do successful
authentication.
On successful authentication, it will
create a security context holder
strategy. Security context holder.
But after that, if you see there is one
success handler on authentication
success.
So, this is
this interface.
So, it has
What it is doing inside this?
Currently, if you see that it hasn't
provided the implementation.
So, it is doing some default clean-up
task. So, I have implemented my
custom or success handler.
And provided on authentication success
implementation.
And in that
what I'm doing is I am in the response,
I am returning the token.
Okay. So, that's what I have just
extended one functionality.
From the same filter
there is a method on authentication
success. So, currently it's calling by
default one which is doing some
clean-up.
So, I have just provided an
implementation of it.
And returning the token in the response
body. So, see that first.
So, that's what I have done. I have
created one custom or two success
handler and implemented it
authentication success handler. And then
provided an override.
I have implemented this one.
So, I have already have the
authentication object, right? This
authentication object has all the info.
Okay. So, from this
or token, I am fetching the ID token
information.
Okay.
So, I'm fetching the ID token
information and putting into the
response.
So, this is the first thing I have done
to make it a stateless.
Okay?
So, I have enhanced this filter,
override one method. So, currently on
success after authentication it is also
doing nothing. I have just enhanced it,
provide a custom implementation,
and in the response added the token.
ID token.
Now, I started the application. And
also, yeah, one more thing.
In the security config,
we have to tell that, right? You have to
use this implementation.
So,
in OAuth 2 login, earlier we were doing
customize with default.
Now, I'm tell that, hey, the success
handler should be this one, the mine
one.
So,
custom OAuth 2 success handler. So, this
is already at the rate component, so
bean object would be created. So, I have
just said that.
When you initialize it, initialize it
with this, not with the default one.
Okay?
And also, I make it a stateless. By
default was if required, we have already
seen that in the previous
um form-based login. By default is this
required. So, we have a specifically
make it that is make it this is a
stateless.
This OAuth 2 login is a stateless,
and this is the success handler which I
want to use.
Okay?
So, now when I started the application,
after authorization from the authen-
authorization server,
see, in response I got this token.
Okay? And now you can Now, only one
thing left.
We have to utilize this token.
And we have to validate it before
providing us
like access to any of the API.
Right?
So, now what we all to do is that now
only one task left is client will pass
this token with every request and we
have to verify it.
Now, let's say the client have to use
the \slash} users.
So, in the authorization they have to
pass bearer token
and this will pass this token.
So, once this token will pass, we have
to validate this ID token, right?
We have to validate this.
So, how to validate that?
So, for that I have created a new
filter.
So, I have created an OAuth validation
filter extend once per request filter.
I've created a filter.
Now, here if you see
first I am doing is extracting the JWT
from the request. So, from authorization
bearer
header, I am fetching the token. This is
ID token which I got.
Now, I am created one utility.
So, this is one utility method that I
have created at the rate component.
So, I have
created one method is token valid. Give
me the token, I will validate it.
So, now what I am doing? How I'm
validating it? Now, see this token is
generated by
GitLab.
And let's say that it has used
this algorithm to sign it.
So, this is an asymmetric encryption.
So, they might have signed it through
private key.
We need its public key.
Okay? And public key URI we have already
sent into the application.properties. If
we just go and recheck our
application.properties
once.
Here, if you see that JWK set URI, this
URL, these are unique for each of the
authorization server.
Okay? So, this is from where we get the
public
key through which we have to sign it.
So,
the first thing I am doing is
I am finding from this token itself who
is the issuer.
Who is the issuer? So, I'm just finding
uh I'm just parsing the token
and taken out like who is the issuer,
whether Git or Auth0 or something else.
Once I get who is the token, I am using
the framework itself, JWT decoder.
We just put from issuer location. We
just provide the location. Here it is a
gitlab.com.
Here it is Auth0 something, whatever the
authorization server.
Now this framework has the understanding
that
uh it will from the
application.properties jwks
it will load the proper authorization uh
server URI.
It will fetch the key.
And from that key, it will decode it,
our JWT. Verify it.
If it is not verified, it will fail it.
Okay? So, we are I'm just utilizing the
framework.
You can even write your own. You can
have the URI. You can read the URI from
application.properties. You can call it
and verify it.
But this is the JWT decoder already does
that. All we have to tell is who is the
issuer.
From that issuer, it will load the URI
from the application.properties
and then decode it for us.
Okay? So, verify and decode for us.
So, what I'm doing is here
after extracting the token, I am
validating the token.
Okay? And it will internally, it will
you know that it will use jwks URI
endpoint to fetch the public key.
And it will validate it.
And once it is validated, I all I am
doing is storing the authentication
object into the security context holder
because without this
login is not successful.
Okay? So, I just created for the testing
purpose, I just created username
password authentication token. I just
put like this is a unique username. And
just put into the security context
holder. Yeah, authentication is success.
Okay? So, this is the filter I have
created.
Now, from the previous video, we know
that we have to add this filter.
So, that's what I'm doing. So, till now
we have seen that we have make it a
stateless, we have added our uh handler,
which is used to return the token in the
response. And now I have added this
filter.
Just before this. So, we we have to
specify the place.
So, now once you start the server now
and hit this endpoint
/users and the bearer token, provide the
token,
you will see that fetch the details
successfully.
So, I'm hitting the login endpoint.
So, let's start the server.
Now, I'm hitting the endpoint.
Click on GitLab.
It is verifying me.
Now, it is asking the username password.
Once I click it,
it will
call the redirecting, right? Redirect
URI.
And from there,
in the response, I am returning the ID
token.
Use the ID token in the header, pass it,
call it,
you will get fetch the details
successfully.
Okay? So,
guys, like if you think that it is too
much information, please go through it
one more time slowly
with your hands.
Things will become little bit more
clear. I try to go in depth as much as
possible
uh
to show you what all thing happening in
background. So, see lot of things
happening in background only.
We are just
seeing that here what internally
happens.
But, lot of thing happen like
seamlessly. We don't even know. We just
click there and everything happens.
Right? So, go through it again slowly
and see that how what to implementation
works.
Okay, guys. Any doubt? Let me know.
We'll discuss further.
Bye.